Wilson McNeil Lowry papers FA1496
Rockefeller Archive Center
Wilson McNeil Lowry papers
1957-1993
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lowry, W. McNeil (Wilson McNeil) (1913-1993)
Ford Foundation
FA1496
3.99 Cubic Feet 10 letter document boxes, 1 half-letter box.
Scope and Contents
The Ford Foundation's Wilson McNeil Lowry papers are a pathway into the Humanities and The Arts effects on America in the 20th century.
The Collection includes: -Reports of Lowry's investments into different art programs -Important speeches and talks for committees and schools -Tributes and Thank you Letters for Lowry's Lifetime commitment to the Humanities and Arts -Personal Letters and Emails with colleagues -Published News Articles (Originals and Copies) -Emails from secretary to pushstart a Lowry Biography Book -Lowry's Memorial Service
Arrangement
The Wilson McNeil Lowry papers are arranged as received.
Biographical / Historical
Born on February 17, 1913 in Columbus, Kansas, Wilson McNeil Lowry is known as the Czar of the Humanities and Arts program. With over 10 years of commitment to the Humanities and Arts, Lowry has transformed American views on the entire industry in his lifetime.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of the RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the RAC through several tranches of records in 2017 and 2018 including gifts from the estate of Marcia Thompson.
- Lowry/Resume, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Lowry/News Clippings, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Lowry/Job Transition and Policies, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Lowry/Presentations and Event Invitations, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Comparisons with a Large Foundation", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Lowry Testimony on National Foundation on the Arts and the Humanities, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Lowry Central Opera Service, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Lowry Association of Independent Colleges of Music, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Lowery Letter to University and Community Arts Administrators, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Lowry Op Ed Page/NY Times, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- The Maryland Institute of Art Remarks, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- The Jo Tyler Lecture, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  General
  At The University of Missouri at Kansas City
- The Economics of Music (Duke University), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Arden House Talk, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Arden House Talk, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- American Council of Learned Societies Interim Proposal, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Library of Congress Symposia on the American Revolution, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- TGC Conference - Toward a Public Policy for the Performing Arts, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- The Performing Arts and American Society - The Fifty-Third American Assembly, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- The Performing Arts and American Society - Final Chapter, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Symposium on Visual Arts (Fort Worth, TX), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- The Art Museum Responsibilities to Society, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Future of the Performing Arts with Questions, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Great Makers, the Arts and Public Policy, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- The Southern Assembly, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Lowry House Appropriations Committee Statement, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- The Mid-America Assembly Report, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- State of the Arts Today, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Mix of Funding Sources and Objectives in the Arts, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Balanchine - The New Yorker Magazine, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- The Past Twenty Years, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Dance/USA Purging the Citadel - II, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Congressman Sidney Yates Address, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Dance/USA Purging the Citadel II, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- The Ford Foundation Economic Survey Speech, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- The New Yorker Profiles (Part I - Lincoln Kirstein), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- The New Yorker Profiles (Part II - Lincoln Kirstein), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- The Americanization of Classical Dance, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Charitable Contributions, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  House Ways and Means Committee Hearings
- "Twenty Years Later", 1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  North Carolina School of the Arts Commencement
- The Arts & Public Policy in the United States, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Creativity and Maturity Evolving Institution Forms, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- "The View From Today" - Tamarind Lithography Workshop Anniversary, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Conversations with Balanchine - The New Yorker, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- The Evolution of Cultural Policy in the U.S., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Humanism and The Humanities - Bellagio Conference, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Northeast Assembly on the Future of the Performing Arts (New Haven), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Orchestral Growth in the 80's - Blessings or Burden?, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Art for All Our Sakes, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- National and Regional Arts Forum, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- The Mix of Funding Sources and Objectives in the Arts Left by the '70s, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- The Economics of the Arts, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Wharton Award, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- The State of The Arts Today - Great Lakes Assembly, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- National and Regional Arts Forum, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Volunteerism is Not For Free, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Howard W. Johnson Statement, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Loose Publications, 1958-1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Loose Documents, 1973-1997 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Loose Publications, 1954-1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Excellence and Equity for the 1980's and Beyond - Discussion Paper, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- National Arts Stabilization Fund, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- National Arts Stabilization Fund, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Lowry Appreciation Letters, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Lowry Award Nominations, 1990-1994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Lowry Book Proposal and Loose Documents, 1959-2016 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Lowry Vision Voice and Personal Documents, 1950-2016 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Additional Perspnal Documents File Included
- Lowry Dance Affiliation Documents with Images, 1959-2011 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  American Literacy Manuscripts Included
- Loose Publications, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Visuals of Lowry's Documents and Reports, 1957-2014 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Lowry Index to Speeches and Lincoln Kirstein Article, 1954-1996 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Lowry Collection Proposal and Speech Index, 2014-2015 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- The Ford Foundation Files, 1957-1974 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Lowry Lament For The Makers (Dramatic Narrative) (Box 5, Folder 8)
- University of Illinois (Lowry Papers Archive), 1996 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Lowry Life Tributes, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- San Francisco Ballet, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Lowry Life Tributes, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Index to Speeches and Articles, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Loose Documents (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Lowry Memorial and Reception, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Lowry Published Article/News Articles, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Archival Reports and Interview Documents, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Loose Documents and Copies, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Letters on Lowery's Impact, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Lowry Bio and News Article, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Chicago Tribune - Lowry Article, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Lowry's Influence on American Life, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- La Mama - Lowry Article, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- American Conservatory Theater Article (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Congressional - Extensions of Remarks, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- In Memory of W. McNeil Lowry, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- San Francisco Chronological - Bio, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- June Wayne - Lowry Memorial Plans, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Scrap Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Resolution of the Board of Trustees, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- National Stabilization Fund Articles, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Presentation Remarks Made to W. McNeil Lowry, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- New York Times - Dance in Review, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Herb Caen - The obit of "Mac" Lowry, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Lowry Important Contacts (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Theatre in France and The American College of Trust and Estate Counsel, 1970-1993 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Report on the Activities of the Fund for Adult Education, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Ford Foundation Principles and Policies Notes, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Increasing Communication Among Peoples Press Document, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- The Humanities and The Private College, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Higher Education and The Individual - Ford Foundation, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Educational Television Docket, 1955-1959 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Institutional Cooperation in Higher Education Research, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Support of the Arts in France, The UK, Denmark, and Italy, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Outline of the Economic and Social Positions, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- The Role of the Foundation in American Society, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- The Economics of the Arts in America (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Music and the Ford Foundation, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- American Federation of Arts Convention Speech, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- The Ford Foundation and The Theatre, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Dedication of the Arena Stage, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- The University and the Creative Arts Talk, 1961; 1962 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Dedication of The Ohio University Fine Arts Building Speech, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- The Ford Foundation and the Creative Arts - North Carolina, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- The Arts and Philanthropy, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- The Foundation and The Arts - Manhattan School of Music Symposium, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Conference on Curatorial Training, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Art and Intensity- The Martha Graham Convocation, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- The Resident Professional Theatre- Ford Foundation, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- The University and Creative Arts II, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Grant and Project Request for Henry Heald, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- National Endowment for The Humanities Part I & II, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Government Policy in the Arts: Report of a Task Force, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Houston Chronicle Article (Nina Vance), 1968 (Box 8, Folder 23)
- New Alley Theatre Dedication, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Ford Foundation Strategy in The Arts - Information Paper, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 25)
- The Economic Crisis in The Arts: The Need for a National Policy, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 26)
- The Arts and The Ford Foundation: Information Paper, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Lowry's Roger Stevens Award Presentation, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Board of Management Retirement Speech, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Lowry - The Maryland Institute, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Lowry's Symposia on the American Revolution, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- The Performing Arts and American Society Book, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Final Report of the Northeast Assembly & The Future of the Performing Arts, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Final Report of The Great Lakes Assembly, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- First Annual John F. Wharton Theatre Award, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- The Arts Public Policy in the United States Book, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Philanthrophy and Culture: The International Foundation Perspective Book, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- The Evolution of Cultural Policy in The United States, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- The Sixty Seventh American Assembly, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- From Patron to President: The View From Inside, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- I Remember Bill Bail Paper, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- The New Yorker Publications, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- San Francisco Ballet and Original News Articles, 1988-1991 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Lowry Handwritten Life Letter, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
- News Articles and Publications, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Life Magazine, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 20)
- Aesthetic Choices and Social Changes: Art Institutions in the 90's, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Conversation with Philip Johnson, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
- About W. McNeil Lowry Pamphlet, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- The Annual Capezio Dance Award and News Articles (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Lowry Memorial Articles and Obituary, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Marcia Thompson Emails for Lowry, 2016 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Memorial Service for: W. McNeil Lowry, 1993; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 28, Tape AV 9994)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  Scope and Contents
  1. Musical Preludes; 2. Tributes; 3. Postlude
- The Awkward Embrace Book, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Communication with Joan Meyers, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Mixed Documents and Personal Letters, 1963-1967 (Box 10, Folder 8)